<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Terminal</title>
    <link>//localhost:1313/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Terminal</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2024 07:07:07 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="//localhost:1313/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Why yet another platform?</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/why-another-platform/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2024 07:07:07 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/why-another-platform/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ever since I was a child, I have always felt the need to document my thoughts and capture fleeting moments of my life. It started as a diary which served the purpose of retrospection (however much is imagineable in the life of a kid) which was of course naive but it helped me develop my writing and formulation skills. In high school, when I decided to go down the path of linguistics, I was required to pass a state examination on literature so there was I consuming the classics of literature and writing god knows how many literary analyses. I was compelled by the literary world and was blessed with a teacher who took my pursuits seriously and indulged me in lengthy discussions on the motives of literary heroes. As I moved into the depth of linguistic academia, the fiction literature was more and more replaced by scientific articles and empirical studies but the need to write migrated to personal notes on my IPhone. In both my linguistic and programming journey, I was genuinely passionate about the discoveries I was making and always tried to relate them to the modern world and my own experiences. I felt the need to share it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Ever since I was a child, I have always felt the need to document my thoughts and capture fleeting moments of my life. It started as a diary which served the purpose of retrospection (however much is imagineable in the life of a kid) which was of course naive but it helped me develop my writing and formulation skills. In high school, when I decided to go down the path of linguistics, I was required to pass a state examination on literature so there was I consuming the classics of literature and writing god knows how many literary analyses. I was compelled by the literary world and was blessed with a teacher who took my pursuits seriously and indulged me in lengthy discussions on the motives of literary heroes. As I moved into the depth of linguistic academia, the fiction literature was more and more replaced by scientific articles and empirical studies but the need to write migrated to personal notes on my IPhone. In both my linguistic and programming journey, I was genuinely passionate about the discoveries I was making and always tried to relate them to the modern world and my own experiences. I felt the need to share it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here comes the main problem: where? It might seem like an irrelevant question but over the years of my postings on Telegram, LinkedIn and Twitter, I realized that it DOES matter (at least to me). A socila media platform shapes the narrative and brings with it certain expectations. While Telegram doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem like a place for thoughts on tech tools at all and is hard to easily share content in a professional setting, LinkedIn feels completely sterile and corporate. Although I&amp;rsquo;ve posted a few things there, I always felt like I had to contain myself not to god forbid fall too far from the context of ultimate corporate masturbation going on on the platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter in this regard appears to be a more suitable place for tech yapping and I appreciate it (although Twitter wars definitely take it too far), still it feels scandalous and attention-seeking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus yours truly with yet another &amp;lsquo;blogging&amp;rsquo; page. I don&amp;rsquo;t indent to promote it or shape an audience, instead I want to create a place free of expectations that would allow me to shape my thoughts in a way that wouldn&amp;rsquo;t imply a certain audience or content form.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
